Guide to the Bob Nelkin Collection of ACC-PARC Records, 1953-2000 MSS 1002
Heinz History Center
- State School and Hospital (SSH) and Interim Care Committee Records, 1972-1997; II.
  - Polk Center, c1966-1997; 3.
    - DPW: Helene Wohlgemuth Regarding Cages at Polk Center Correspondence III, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 19)
      - Letter from Marian Bromeley to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 21, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 19, Item 5)
        A letter from Marian Bromeley to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth supporting her actions at Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Bonnie Pribich to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 25, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 19, Item 6)
        A letter from Bonnie Pribich to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth supporting her actions at Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Margaret Kunzman to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 22, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 19, Item 7)
        A letter from Margaret Kunzman to Helene Wohlgemuth regarding the conditions at Polk State School and Hospital and care for individuals with developmental and intellectual disabilities.
      - Letter from Mrs. Thanos to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 25, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 19, Item 8)
        A letter from Mrs. D. L. Thanos, the sister of a Polk State School and Hospital resident, to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth regarding the firing of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk. Thanos believes that Wohlgemuth acted too hastily, without proper knowledge of the needs of the residents of Polk State School and Hospital. Thanos also touches upon the problems of overcrowding and funding at Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Eugene and Marilyn Witherup to Milton Shapp, April 23, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 19, Item 9)
        A letter from Eugene and Marilyn Witherup to Governor Milton Shapp regarding the removal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital. Mr. and Mrs. list the problems with alternatives to the cages/pens, the need for more funding and staffing, and speak of Dr. McClelland's commitment to residents.
      - Letter from Adah M. Armstrong to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 25, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 19, Item 10)
        A letter from Adah Armstrong to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth denouncing her decision to remove Dr. James McClelland as superintendent at Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Three Nurses to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 19, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 19, Item 11)
        A letter from three nurses: Beth Dunham, Mary Karr, and Rosemarie Skiba to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth voicing their disapproval of the Secretary's actions at Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from George Moyer to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 24, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 19, Item 12)
        A letter from George Moyer to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth regarding the use of cages at Polk State School and Hospital that led to Wohlgemuth's removal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of the institution.
      - Letter from Francis Rogan to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 25, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 19, Item 13)
        A letter from Francis Rogan, mayor of New Castle and father of a resident of Polk State School and Hospital, protesting the dismissal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk.
      - Letter from Dr. James Clifford to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 20, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 19, Item 14)
        A letter from Dr. James Clifford to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth regarding Wohlgemuth's decision to remove Dr. James McClelland as superintendent at Polk State School and Hospital. Clifford, who interned under McClelland twenty years ago, believes that McClelland's dismissal was a mistake and that he is a competent and compassionate physician.
      - Letter from John Fidorek to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 1973 (Box 4, Folder 19, Item 15)
        A letter from John. Fidorek, a parent of a Polk State School and Hospital resident, to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth, disagreeing with Wohlgemuth's actions at Polk.
      - Letter from Ann Novosel to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 24, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 19, Item 16)
        A letter from Ann Novosel to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth regarding the removal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent at Polk State School and Hospital. Novosel requests for McClelland's reinstatement and discusses the issues of funding and overcrowding at state institutions.
      - Anonymous Letter to Dr. James McClelland, April 18, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 19, Item 17)
        An unsigned letter to Dr. James McClelland from the parent of a Polk State School and Hospital resident. The author expresses their support to McClelland and questions the qualifications and character of Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth.
      - Letter from Mrs. Campbell to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 18, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 19, Item 18)
        A letter from Mrs. Campbell to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth regarding the removal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital. Campbell calls the dismissal a misjudgment and requests for McClelland's reinstatement.
    - DPW: Helene Wohlgemuth Regarding Cages at Polk Center Correspondence IV, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20)
      - Letter from Marjorie Felder to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 23, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 1)
        A letter from Marjorie Felder to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth questioning her reasons for dismissing Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Beatrice McClelland to Milton Shapp, April 24, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 2)
        A letter from Beatrice McClelland, a former employee at Polk State School and Hospital, to Governor Milton Shapp, denouncing the dismissal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of the institution and the actions taken by Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth and PARC members.
      - Letter from Catherine Groetzinger to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 24, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 3)
        A letter to Helene Wohlgemuth from Catherine Groetzinger, a parent of a Polk State School and Hospital resident, expressing dissatisfaction with Wohlgemuth and her decision to remove Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk.
      - Letter from James Gemmell to Milton Shapp, April 24, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 4)
        A letter from James Gemmell, president of Clarion State College, to Governor Milton J. Shapp regarding the dismissal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital. Gemmell speaks highly of Dr. McClelland and advises for his reinstatement.
      - Letter from Helen Shawkey to Milton Shapp, April 24, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 5)
        A letter from Helen Shawkey to Governor Milton Shapp announcing the Polk Borough Council's opposition to the dismissal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Robert Carone to Milton Shapp, April 25, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 6)
        A letter from Robert Carone, executive director of the Family Service and Children's Aid Society, to Governor Milton Shapp disapproving of the dismissal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - "Welfare Chief Back on Polk" Article, April 24, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 7)
        A Pittsburgh Press article regarding Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth's knowledge of the cages used to restrain residents of Polk State School and Hospital. This clipping contains notations from an unidentified person that criticizes the actions of Wohlgemuth.
      - "Association Backs McClelland: State Bans Use of Cages, Pens" Article, April 25, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 8)
        A Pittsburgh Post-Gazette article regarding the support Dr. James McClelland received from the association of State Mental Hospital Physicians following his dismissal as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital. This clipping contains notations from an unidentified parent of a resident criticizing McClelland's removal.
      - Letter from Mrs. Wesley S. to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 9)
        A letter from Mrs. Wesley S., a parent of a Polk State School and Hospital resident, to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth criticizing her decision to remove Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk.
      - Letter from Louise Sherman to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 10)
        A letter from Louise Sherman, the daughter of a former preacher at Polk State School and Hospital, to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth regarding the removal of Dr. McClelland as superintendent of Polk. Sherman defends McClelland and believes that Wohlgemuth was unfair to him.
      - Letter from Ann Wright to Milton Shapp, April 23, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 11)
        A letter from Ann Wright to Governor Milton Shapp protesting the "inhumane treatment" of Dr. James McClelland at Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Violet K. to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 23, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 12)
        A letter from Violet K., the mother of a Polk State School and Hospital resident, to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth thanking her for her actions at the institution.
      - Letter from Mrs. Eugene S. to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 13)
        A letter from Mrs. Eugene S., the parent of a Polk State School and Hospital resident, to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth criticizing her for her decision to remove Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk.
      - Letter from Cottage "A" Residents, April 19, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 14)
        A letter from the residents of Cottage "A" at Polk State School and Hospital, written by Mary Sydoriak, questioning Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth's actions, the dismissal of Dr. James McClelland, and the removal of the cages used to restrain residents.
      - Letter from Mary K. to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 23, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 15)
        A letter from Mary K., the mother of a Polk State School and Hospital resident, to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth disapproving of the removal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital. Mary K. believes that Dr. Wesley White is not the right choice for an interim superintendent, and requests for an unbiased investigation.
      - Letter from Thomas Snyder to Milton Shapp, April 20, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 16)
        A letter from Thomas Snyder to Governor Milton Shapp expressing his belief that Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth was manipulated by PARC to take action at Polk State School and Hospital that she should not have.
      - Letter from Clarence Baldwin to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 23, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 17)
        A letter from Clarence W. Baldwin, the pastor of the First United Methodist Church of Franklin, Pennsylvania, to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth disapproving of the removal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Anonymous Letter to Patricia Clapp, April 23, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 18)
        An anonymous letter to PARC President Patricia Clapp, mistakenly addressed as Secretary of Welfare, denouncing the removal of the cages at Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Joseph H. to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 23, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 19)
        A letter from Joseph H., the father of a Polk State School and Hospital resident, to Helene Wohlgemuth. Mr. H. gives Wohlgemuth a letter that he sent to several newspapers supporting Dr. James McClelland and his son's treatment at Polk.
      - Letter from Thomas Snyder to the Department of Public Welfare, April 20, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 20)
        A letter from Thomas Snyder asking for the reinstatement of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital. Snyder defends McClelland and speaks highly of his service at Polk.
      - Letter from Don Bashline to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 19, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 21)
        A letter from Dr. Don Bashline to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth protesting the dismissal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Josephine McCracken to Milton Shapp, April 23, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 22)
        A letter from Josephine McCracken, a resident of Venango County and a staff member of a Venango County Health and Welfare agency, to Secretary Helene McCracken regarding the dismissal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Franklin Residents to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 19, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 23)
        A letter from a group of Franklin, PA residents to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth denouncing the dismissal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Copy of a Telegram from E. G. Pearce Jr. to Milton Shapp, April 23, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 24)
        A telegram from E. G. Pearce Jr., executive director of the Samuel Justus Charitable Trust, to Governor Milton Shapp demanding the reinstatement of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Robert Pilewski to Milton Shapp, April 23, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 25)
        A letter from Robert Pilewski, president of the Venango County Medical Society, to Governor Milton Shapp criticizing the dismissal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Mrs. Elliston to Milton Shapp, April 18, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 26)
        A letter from Mrs. Elliston to Governor Milton Shapp requesting for the reinstatement of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Note from Barbara Fruchter to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 18, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 27)
        A brief note from Barbara Fruchter to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth congratulating her on her actions and decision to remove Dr. James McClelland as superintendent after her visit to Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Steve Martin to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 18, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 28)
        A letter from Steve Martin to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth commending her for her actions at Polk State School and Hospital and hopes that the "surprise visits" and her work improving state welfare institutions will continue.
      - Anonymous Letter to Helene Wohlgemuth (2), April 18, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 29)
        An anonymous letter to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth thanking her for her actions at Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from a Former Warren State Hospital Patient to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 12, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 30)
        A letter from a former Warren State Hospital patient to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth thanking her for her actions at Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from a Polk State School and Hospital Employee to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 31)
        A letter from an unidentified Polk State School and Hospital employee to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth regarding other employees who may not be qualified for their positions and requests Wohlgemuth to investigate claims of child abuse at the institution.
      - Letter from Earl Nielliger to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 32)
        A letter from Earl Nielliger, recreation chairman at the Lancaster Association for Retarded Children, to Helene Wohlgemuth thanking her for her actions at Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Janet Seale to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 19, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 33)
        A letter to Janet Seale, the sister of a man with Downs Syndrome, and a special education teacher, to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth. Seale thanks Wohlgemuth for her actions to remove the cages and expresses gratitude that someone cares enough to investigate and improve Pennsylvania's state institutions.
      - Letter from Ann Johnson to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 19, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 34)
        A letter from Ann Johnson, a college student who has worked as a Child Care Aid Trainee at Polk State School and Hospital the three previous summers to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth. Johnson congratulates Wohlgemuth on her actions, but brings awareness to other issues that she believes contributes to the poor conditions at Polk.
      - Letter from Catherine Ostrsycki to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 35)
        A letter from Catherine Ostrsycki to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth congratulating her on her surprise visits and decisive action at Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Karen King to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 20, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 36)
        A letter from Karen King to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth congratulating her on her actions at Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Mrs. Wood to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 19, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20, Item 37)
        A letter from Mrs. M. Wood to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth supporting her actions at Polk State School and Hospital. Wood also encourages Wohlgemuth to visit other state institutions and continue to improve the conditions at those institutions.
    - DPW: Helene Wohlgemuth Regarding Cages at Polk Center Correspondence V, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 21)
      - Letter from Mrs. R. to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 17, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 21, Item 1)
        A letter from Mrs. R., the mother of a child with developmental and intellectual disabilities, to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth thanking her for her actions to improve conditions at state institutions.
      - Letter from Emil Barth to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 19, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 21, Item 2)
        A letter from Emil Barth to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth listing the poor conditions at state institutions he visited and recommends Wohlgemuth to visit more institutions to improve conditions.
      - Letter from Ann Vaughan to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 21, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 21, Item 3)
        A letter from Ann Vaughan to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth congratulating her on uncovering deplorable conditions at state institutions. Vaughan also voices her opinion on the appointment of Frederick T. Trump to the board of trustees of Danville State Hospital.
      - Letter from Orville P. to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 20, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 21, Item 4)
        A letter from Orville P. to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth thanking her for investigating and taking action at Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Robert McGill to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 18, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 21, Item 5)
        A letter from Robert McGill, a former employee at Polk State School and Hospital, to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth. McGill commends Wohlgemuth for her decision to remove Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk and recounts his experiences at the institution.
      - Letter from Dr. J. Howard Turner to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 19, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 21, Item 6)
        A letter from Dr. J. Howard Turner of the University of Pittsburgh's Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth regarding the removal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital. Turner requests Wohlgemuth to reconsider her decision.
      - Letter from Elise Nystrom to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 23, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 21, Item 7)
        A letter from Elise Nystrom to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth disagreeing with her actions at Polk State School and Hospital to remove the cages used to restrain residents and to remove Dr. James McClelland as superintendent.
      - Letter from Mrs. Davis to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 23, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 21, Item 8)
        A letter from Mrs. Davis to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth disagreeing with Wohlgemuth's actions at Polk State School and Hospital to remove the cages used to restrain residents and the dismissal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent.
      - Letter from Dorothy Murphy to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 22, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 21, Item 9)
        A letter from Dorothy Murphy to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth demanding the reinstatement of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Elma Harvey to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 17, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 21, Item 10)
        A letter from Elma Harvey, a former Lakeside employee at Polk State School and Hospital, to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth regarding the removal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk. Harvey accuses others at Polk of manipulating McClelland.
      - Letter from a "Concerned Parent" to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 23, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 21, Item 11)
        An anonymous letter from a "concerned parent" to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth expressing distrust for her and her actions at Polk State School and Hospital to remove the cages used to restrain residents and to remove Dr. James McClelland as superintendent.
      - Letter from J. K. Runge to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 20, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 21, Item 12)
        A letter from J. K. Runge, a former Polk State School and Hospital employee, to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth regarding the methods used by employees at Polk. Runge believes that the methods used at Polk are in the best interest of the residents.
      - Letter from Carol Baugh to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 24, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 21, Item 13)
        A letter from Carol Baugh to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth requesting for the reinstatement of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from the Venango County Commissioners to Milton Shapp, April 24, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 21, Item 14)
        A letter from the Venango County Commissioners to Governor Milton Shapp requesting for the reinstatement of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital. The commissioners outline the options available to protect residents and believe that cages are the best option.
      - Letter from a Westmoreland County Resident to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 23, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 21, Item 15)
        An anonymous letter from a "taxpayer of Westmoreland County" to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth criticizing Wohlgemuth's actions at Polk State School and Hospital to remove the cages used to restrain residents and to remove Dr. James McClelland as superintendent.
      - Erie Association for Retarded Children Statement on the Dismissal of Dr. James McClelland, April 24, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 21, Item 16)
        A letter from Mrs. Lubecki, president of the Erie Association for Retarded Children, to Secretary Wohlgemuth explaining the association's stance regarding the dismissal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Hugh Ransom to Milton Shapp, April 19, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 21, Item 17)
        A letter from Hugh Ransom, executive director of the United Cerebral Palsy of Pennsylvania, to Governor Milton Shapp, requesting the reinstatement of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital and an investigation into his dismissal.
      - Letter from William Cavanaugh to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 19, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 21, Item 18)
        A letter from William Cavanaugh, an Erie attorney, to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth condemning her decision to remove Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from William Cavanaugh to Milton Shapp, April 19, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 21, Item 19)
        A letter from William Cavanaugh, an Erie attorney, to Governor Milton Shapp condemning Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth's decision to remove Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
    - DPW: Helene Wohlgemuth Regarding Cages at Polk Center Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 22)
      - Letter from Robert Heasley to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 19, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 22, Item 1)